A Guide to the Dorothy Alexander Architectural Collection, 1934-1994
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Dorothy Alexander Architectural Collection, 1934-1994
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2008-089
3.1 cu. ft. 15 boxes
Dorothy Alexander was educated at the McGill University Architectural School in Montreal. She worked for several firms including Wurster, Bernardi, and Emmons Architects before starting her own firm in 1961. The collection consists primarily of drawings, sketches, and building specifications for buildings designed by the architect Dorothy Alexander. Projects include remodeling work for the Arriflex Corporation, Lowel-Light Manufacturing, as well as several houses designed and built in California.
Alexander, Dorothy Baxter
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Dorothy Alexander Architecture Collection was donated to the IAWA here in Special Collections in 2008.
Biographical Information
Dorothy Dusty Baxter Alexander was educated at the McGill University Architectural School in Montreal. She started work for the architect, John Carl Warnecke in February, 1955. She later worked for the firm Wurster, Bernardi, and Emmons before starting her own firm in April of 1961. Her architectural credits include commercial remodelling for the Arriflex Corporation, Lowel-Light Manufacturing, Panavision and the Jack Tilton Gallery. She has also done restoration work on housing, as well as, designed houses and duplexes in the San Francisco area.
Alexander also works as a photographer. In 1981, Alexander became a staff photographer for Skyline, the magazine for the Institute for Architecture and Urban Studies. During the 1980s through the early 1990s, she worked as a photographer for The Writer's Voice, The Academy of American Poets, West Side Spirit, and the Toronto Globe & Mail. Since the late 1980s Alexander worked as a photographer for Oculus, the magazine for the New York Chapter of the American Institute of Architects.
Alexander's photographs have been the subjects of numerous exhibitions in New York. They focus on urban landscapes, street portraits, and some abstract work. Her work is in the main collections at the Bibliotheque Nationale de Paris and the National Portrait Gallery in Washington, DC.
Scope and Content
The collection consists primarily of Alexander's works as an architect. This includes building plans and specifications for work done for the Arriflex Corporation, Lowel-Light Manufacturing, and the Jack Tilton Gallery, as well as many other projects. The collection also includes blueprints for building designed by Alexander while working for the architectural firms of Wurster, Bernardi, and Emmons Architects and James Baker and Peter Blake Architects. Other materials include a curriculum vitae, correspondence, and an article about Alexander published in the San Francisco Examiner.
Arrangement
The collection is separated into two series. Series I consists of biographical materials and drawings done by Dorothy Alexander as an independent architect. Series II consists of blueprints drawn by Dorothy Alexander while working for other firms. Drawings and other materials are arranged in chronological order.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also the Dorothy Alexander Photographs, 1974 (0.1 cu. ft.) in IAWA Small Collections Ms2009-054.
Index Terms
Subjects:
International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA)
Contents List
- Biographical Information and Independent Projects, 1939-1994
  - Biographical Materials and Publications
    - Biographical Information, 1964-1967 (Box-folder 1:5)
    - The Liveable City, October 1989, Number 12/2 (Contains photographs by Alexander) (Folder 1)
    - Exhibition Poster (Gotham Book Mart Gallery), 1995? (Folder 1)
  - Sinsheimer House, August 1939-May31, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Grover House, July 1954 - August 14, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Grover House - Correspondence, October 16, 1961-November 28, 1961 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Alexander House/Office, June 17, 1957-January 2, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Alexander House, undated (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Calhoun House, September 23, 1958-April 28, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Beach House, September 3, 1959 - May 26, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Beach House, June 18, 1964 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Cannery Row, July 28, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Breck Street Properties, August 11, 1961 - September 5, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Sinsheimer Olive Street Apartments - Phase I, December 11, 1961 - July 1, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Views Land Company, January 28, 1962 - May 9, 1963 (Box 4)
    - 106b Second Street, January 28, 1962 - May 9, 1963 (Box 4)
    - 99 and 101 Marion Avenue, June 19, 1962 (Box 4)
    - 103 and 105 Marion Avenue, June 19, 1962 (Box 4)
    - 118 A and B West Street, May 8, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Bennett Valley - Job 160, undated (Box 4)
    - Unidentified Views Land Company Projects (Box 5)
  - Wright House, May 2, 1962 - September 10, 1964 (Box 5)
  - House 223 and 224 Sausalito Bay Land Company, May 26, 1962 - March 26, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Jacobsen House, June 2-8, 1962 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Robbins House, June 3, 1962 - April 30, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Sinsheimer Olive Street Apartments - Phase II, November 5, 1962 - February 20, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Bowen House, November 16, 1962 - May 12, 1964 (Box 6)
    - Bowen House, undated (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Martinez House, March 22, 1963 - June 13, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Daniels House, April 11, 1963 - July 9, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Houses at 512, 514, and 516 South Street, June 18, 1963 (Box 7)
  - Shaffner House, July 24, 1963 - December 29, 1968 (Box 7)
    - Shaffner House, July 10, 1964-January 26, 1995 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Schlesinger House, October 10, 1963 - June 16, 1965 (Box 7)
  - Godfrey House, February 21, 1964 (Box 8)
  - Farrow House, September 25, 1964 - October 29, 1964 (Box 8)
  - Radio Station KPFA, June 11, 1966 - June 11, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Steiner Office, October 1966 (Box 8)
  - Sinsheimer Brothers Annex, January 18-28, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Tony Smith Cigarette, March 24, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Forman House, May 9, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Goberman House, August 7, 1974 (Box 9)
  - Lowell-Light Manufacturing, October 29, 1979 - January 8, 1980 (Box 9)
  - Arriflex Corporation, June 9, 1980 - May 27, 1997 (Box 9)
  - Tilton Gallery, September 17, 1985 - February 28, 1990 (Box 9)
  - Arriflex Corporation at the Camera Service Center, April 27, 1987 - April 27, 1994 (Box 10)
  - Lowell Family Addition, undated (Box 11)
  - Shean House, undated (Box 11)
  - Unidentified Sketches and Drawings, undated (Box 11)
  - Second Street Studies, undated (Box-folder 1:7)
- Other Architectural Firms, 1959-1968
  - Wurster, Bernardi, and Emmons Architects:
    - New Family Quarters for Point Reyes Light Station, September 3, 1959 (Box 12)
    - F.M. Transmitter Building for Crocker Land Company, May 16-24, 1960 (Box 13)
    - Building for Mason Wells and Frank Hamilton, October 17, 1960 (Box 14)
  - James Baker and Peter Blake Architects:
    - Eckstein Residence, May 13, 1968 (Box 15)